Hello, everyone, and
welcome back to our
series of lectures
on renal physiology.
And by this time, I hope
you've finished looking
at the transport of
all the electrolytes,
vital electrolytes, save
for protons and bicarbonate,
which we will go over in
the next lecture. But today
we will be talking about
the transport of metabolites
and components of metabolism,
mainly the transport
of urea, glucose, and
collectively organic solutes.
So again, let's start
off with a scenario.
And in this case,
you're, you know, you're
doing your first week in EM.
And a young girl
was brought to your,
brought into the
ER by her parents.
She's 12 years old.
She's an athlete,
healthy 12 year old,
and absolutely, you
know, and a healthy
athletic 12 year old.
But suddenly, in the
last two months, she's
turned into a completely
different person. She
is lethargic, she can
barely get out of bed,
she's easily fatigued,
their young girl,
their parents are just
beside themselves.
She's lost a lot of weight,
and they say like her
schoolwork is suffering
because she's not focused.
uh so taking your history
you know that you you
you are told that she is
she can't stop going to
the bathroom she goes to
the bathroom 12 to 13 times
a day uh and she she's
like constantly drinking
water and complaining
of being thirsty uh her
physical examinations reveal
signs of dehydration. So
there's something going
on with her fluid status.
When you actually ask
them to collect urine for
24-hour urine quantification,
you see that she's
excreting a very, very
high amount of fluids,
seven and a half liters a
day, when normal average
anywhere between 0.8 and 1
.5 liters. And then you do
analysis of her urine, just,
you know, simple urinalysis,
significantly proteinuria.
The urine is remarkably
glycosiuric. There's
a lot of sugars,
you know, glucose in the urine,
and the blood test doesn't
really you know at that
instant just shows normal
glycemia but uh but
it's it's just atypical
and you start thinking how
these things could be related
so fatigue lethargy
frequent urination thirst
and sugar and urine
that's the that's the main
relationships that
you're looking for.
So these are our objectives.
So hopefully by the end
of the session, we can talk
about the renal processes
undergoing the regulation
of glucose urea and uric
acid, and then the same with
proteins of oligopeptides
and amino acids, and
then looking at organic
collectively, just a big
group of compounds that we'll
put under the umbrella of
either an organic acid or
an organic base. And what
is the significance of
these organic base and organic
acid secretory systems.
So we'll start
off with glucose.
So
maintenance of plasma
glucose and glucose
regulation is
incredibly important.
And our kidneys end up,
you know, we want to save
all our glucose for metabolic
reasons. You don't to
get rid of and you know of
of of your plasma glucose
who's anybody who's
ever felt who's ever had
hypoglycemia can attest to
that um there are or you know
our brain exclusively uses
glucose as a fuel source
and any kind of a loss
um or decreases in plasma
glucose and glucose
availability has central nervous
system effects, cognitive
effects, and if you've never,
you know, if you've ever
become hypoglycemic, had
a hypoglycemic episode,
you can really experience
and feel that is thinking
becomes very, very difficult.
So glucose is regulated
by primarily by insulin
and a variety of other
hormones. We're not
going to talk a lot about
them in these lectures
of endocrinology. When
we do endocrinology,
we'll get the full
breakdown of it.
However, glucose, again,
it's not bound to anything
in the plasma. There's no
plasma binding to proteins,
and it's freely filtered
in the glomerulus.
Again, 100% filtration
And the wonderful
thing about glucose,
which makes it a lot
simpler, is almost the
entirety of the amount
that's filtered.
The filtered load of
glucose is reabsorbed
in the proximal
convoluted tubule.
The other sections of the
nephron do very little. I'm
not going to say it never
happens, but 99% of it
is taken away in the proximal
convoluted tubule, and
the rest is done in the
other sections of the distal
nephron, the thick ascending
limbs, the collecting
tubules, and the dorsal
collecting tubules, and the
collecting ducts, to the
point that in a healthy
individual, you will not have
any glucose in your urine.
So where does your
absorption occur? Well, as I
said, it occurs in the
proximal convoluted tubules.
And it's absorbed by
two members of this
family of co-transporters
called the sodium
glucose co-transporters,
SGLT1 1 and SGLT2.
So again, they're found
in the proximal tubule.
S1 segment of the proximal
convoluted tubule is
rich in SGLT2. Again,
these two are, these, these
trans, these co-transporters
are found on the apical
side, right? So this is
where we get filtration.
And uses, glucose gets
taken into the cell,
piggybacking on the
concentration gradient
developed by, remember
who, our old friend,
the sodium-potassium ATPase.
The concentration
gradient for sodium will
drive the transport of
glucose into the cytosol.
SGL2 is the isoform
that is most responsible
for the majority of
glucose reabsorption in the
S1 segment of the proximal
convoluted tubule.
in the S3 segment and
probably the latter parts
of the S2 segment, once
you get to the proximal
straight tubule, the
isoform changes. Instead of
SGL2, you have SGLT1. The
difference between them
is even though they're
both on the apical side,
the stoichiometry changes.
So it moves two molecules
of sodium from one molecule
of glucose. So it'll create
a gradient better than
across the apical
membrane than it does any
other section. Why is
this important? Well,
this is a target
of a novel class of
compounds. These are
called the group uretics.
Initially, they were
developed for the treatment
of type 2 diabetes, but
it's been found that they
have remarkably, they are
remarkably efficacious
in the treatment of
congestive heart failure.
And to the point that,
you know, I've spoken to
cardiologists and they say
they are just basically putting
almost all their patients
on SGL2 inhibitors because
of its beneficial effects.
I don't think, I haven't
seen anything lately about
what the proposed mechanism,
why is it so good? Because
these effects, it seems
like they're independent
on the effects on glucose
excretion. And it's not really
clear 100% what is going
on to make the heart pump
better in this context.
They don't think it's got to
do with water load management.
But again, I haven't done
the latest literature review.
Excuse me. So once the
glucose gets into the
cytosol, it gets reabsorbed
back into the basolateral
side by glucose channels.
And these are the glute
channels. They are
different. The glutes are
different than the SGLTs.
Let's just remember that.
Glutes are channels
for glucose.
There is no co
-transporter activity.
And also, they're on
the opposite side.
They are not on the
apical side, they're
only found on the
basolateral side. So it's
very important to
make that distinction.
They're sodium
dependent and they
remove glucose in a
facilitated manner.
Now, you know, it's
one of the reasons
that so much of it is
reabsorbed, 100% of
it, is to do, it has
to do with the brush
border of the proximal
convoluted tubules.
This massive increase in
surface area has a lot of
SGL2 inhibition, excuse
me, SGL2 transporters.
You know, so you can just
see very clearly, just by
the surface area component
of it, that why you
can have such extensive
reabsorption of glucose,
again, to the point that
you almost don't need any
more reabsorption once
you get past these stages.
How about, you know, so
what is going on with urine
excretion? So maybe we can
talk about the titration
curves when we are
talking in this context
between the relationships
between glucose and the
plasma and the rates of
glucose reabsorption. And
in this case, in this graph,
in this glucose titration
curve, this is done by
looking at via an infusion
of glucose. So not a
one-time load like you
would have if you ate a
piece of cake. You would
have an IV infusing glucose
at a determinable rate.
So one of the things that
we always have to remember,
a low filtered load of
glucose, anything that's
lower than 200 milligrams
per deciliter, is completely
reabsorbed. We have no
glucose found in the urine.
So the clearance is
complete. And you can see
that here. If you look
at the filtered load upon
infusion, right? So this
is the concentration.
And the more you infuse,
the more the filtered
load becomes. It
keeps going on in a
linear manner. You can
just say like in a 200,
in the first 10 minutes,
200 in, you know,
it's basically exactly
the same amount per
unit of time, constant
infusion. And you can
see that the delivery
to the Bowman's
capsule is also linear.
Once you get past
the threshold,
though, the
relationships change.
So the threshold is
relatively low for infusion.
It's about 200 milligrams
per deciliter, which
is higher than normal
plasma glucose. Our plasma
glucose is around 100
milligrams in a healthy
person going up to the
high 100s before you
get to 200 if in a non
-insulin-dependent person.
And that's partly why
people are not diabetic
when insulin resistance
or the lack of
insulin is ends up what's
driving the increases
in plasma glucose,
right? So healthy people
do not excrete any
glucose in the urine.
But even people with
diabetes mellitus,
the glucose urea doesn't really
occur until 200 milligrams
per deciliter, until
the threshold. And this
is the plasma threshold
that's indicated here.
And you could measure
that because not only is
the urine, not only is
glucose being infused,
but also glucose is being
released in the urine,
being excreted at almost
the same rate that
it is getting infused,
until you get to the
threshold. Then you start
getting a shift. And
the first part of it, as
you go higher than the
threshold,
you start getting a change
in the slope up until
around 400, where you
reach a plateau. And this
plateau is called the
transport maximum, the TM.
So glucose will hit its TM
at around 400 milligrams per
minute. And this TM is an
indicator that our apical
transporters are fully
saturated, that there is no
available free transporters
left. So any glucose that makes
it past the Bowman's capsule
will end up remaining in
the nephron and being
excreted. And if you remember,
the nephrons have
very low capacity for
reabsorbing glucose
after you leave the
proximal convoluted
tubule. So that's why
you'll have glucose
remaining in the urine.
There is a lot of
differences among nephrons in
one person, within
different kidneys, and of
course in the population.
And the filtered load
of nephrons can be dependent
on a lot of different
things. of densities
of the SGLTs along the
proximal tubule, the
size of the glomerulus.
Obviously, if you have
more glomerulus, you'll,
you know, if you have a
bigger glomerulus, you
have more surface area.
So you have a more of a
filtered load and that
filtered load, the higher
the filtered load can
have different effects.
So there's a, you know,
the person to person,
there's a, there's a big
variability in the, um,
the, the, the
mechanisms that are,
that, that, that
affect glucose.
And that's really about,
that's it, you know, that's
the final thing about
glucose. So if we're going to
think about in terms of, uh,
metabolites, uh, the next
Next, one that we have
to look at that is very
important in context of
renal function is urea.
And what is urea and
where do we get urea from?
Well, urea is very important.
It's obviously the
namesake of the hepatic
urea cycle, which is
one of the main ways we
get rid of ammonium,
ammonium ion in our body.
So an ammonium ion is the
primary nitrogenous waste
of amino acid catabolism,
the breakdown of amino
acids. In the urea cycle you
can see here that urea can
bind with bicarbonate to
give you ornithine, which
is an amino acid, but not
an essential amino acid.
It's not really used that
much in protein synthesis.
What it does, it gives up a
phosphate to turn
into citrulline.
Citrulline is another amino
acid, and citrulline will
leave the mitochondria and
go into the Well, it'll
interact with aspartate to
give you arginine. Arginine
is, you know, and arginine
can either be metabolized
to urea or enter any kind
of a synthetic pathway.
Another component of
the breakdown of the
molecule that's made
from aspartate and
citrulline, that is
arginosuccinate, is fumarate,
and that enters the
citric acid cycle,
and ornithine then can
recycle back into the
mitochondria to re-enter
the cycle again. And
so it just keeps its
gives its own substrate in
order to drive it. And
where would you get
ammonia from? Well,
ammonia, you get it from
breakdown of amino acids,
amino acid metabolism.
You know, glutamate
is straightforward
biochemistry, but
ammonium ion is a
big component of
amino acid balance.
And you can see here,
when you have something
like glutamic acid, it
can get converted by
losing an ammonium to
alpha-ketoglutarate.
If you remember, alpha
-ketoglutarate can then
enter the Krebs cycle.
If you add, you know,
if that today, I'm sorry,
if you, or if you add
ammonium to alpha
-ketoglutarate, You can make
glutamate, and then glutamate
can be metabolized to
glutamine by another
ammonium. Again, the point
is ammonium is a big part
of amino acid balance.
So these products can
change depending on the
availability of amino acids.
So why is urea important?
Well, you know, first, a couple
of things. Urea is small,
60 Daltons. It's very polar,
and it's water-soluble.
Normal plasma concentrations,
we always have some
degree of urea in our blood.
And again, because we're
constantly breaking down
proteins, it's a waste
product to be excreted. and
more so it is critical for
water regulation and salt
reabsorption. I'll talk
about how urea is important
in this process in the
lecture about concentration
ability of the kidney.
The primary route of
excretion is in the
urine. There's some
via sweat and stool.
It's freely filtered
at the glomerulus,
100%. You reabsorb
a lot of it, and
then you secrete a
substantial amount.
So reabsorbed, then they
secrete. So the amount
that we always find in
the urine is more than the
amount filtered because of
that secreted component.
Normal levels of urea
are not toxic because
we measure it, and we
measure it in our blood
as blood urea, not
nitrogen. That's one of
the important, and it's
one of the important
components of a basic
metabolic panel. You probably
remember that probably
from some of your CBL
-calsic cases. And you can
see that it's very much
dependent. It's a very,
you get a big range of
BUN values. So I can't
think of anything else that
can double in terms of
laboratory diagnostics.
You can correct me, but
right off the top of
my head, I can't think
of anything that if
you double the lowest
amount, you won't have.
It's not considered
pathological, right even
potassium if you have 4.4
milligrams per deciliter
um and you double it you
know 8.8 that's dangerous
you don't want to have
that high sodium you know
if you have 110 if you
go to 220 that's high you
don't want that um but
not so much with bun but
bun you have a um large
standard deviation you
have a large amount that
that you can um that you
can manipulate and um
mainly because, you know,
again, you can make a
lot of it and get rid of
it and or reuse it. So
it's the control that's
based on the amounts
that it's metabolized.
So as you can see,
the majority, a large part
of the filtered load of urea
is reabsorbed in the proximal
convoluted tubule, not
so much as you would find
with bicarbonate or glucose.
Bicarbonate and glucose
are almost completely
reabsorbed. Urea is about
50% of it reabsorbed, but a
substantial amount is secreted
back into the nephron, and
then whatever is left is
reabsorbed in the medullary
collecting duct to the point
that the amount of urea found
in urine is about 50% of
the filtered load of urea.
Reabsorption is done
by the concentration
gradient, and that
is what drives most,
almost, that's what
drives urea reabsorption.
Some of the things that can
affect reabsorption like
potassium, like sodium,
changes in urine flow are very,
very important. So the more
urine flow you have, the
higher your urea excretion.
That could, you know, that
could be seen clinically.
It's one of the things
that you would see with if
there is excesses in BUN above
the normal ranges. A simple
way is to give somebody
an IV and hydrate them and
increase the urine flow.
And if you increase urine
flow, you end up reabsorbing
less water and urea, and
you can filter a lot more.
And vice versa is when
you have decreased
urine flow. If you
have progressive renal
disease, if you're severely
dehydrated, and your
renal blood flow and
GFR drop, and then urine
flow drops, you can
have urea retention, and
then increases in blood,
urea, and nitrogen.
So what are the
transport mechanisms?
In the proximal tubule,
it's paracellular.
It's either done by solvent
drag, piggybacking on water,
or the concentration gradient
of urea compared to plasma.
So you get a favorable
gradient to promote uptake.
into thin descending limb
and ascending limb, an
equal amount that's
reabsorbed is secreted back
into the loop of Henle. And
this is done translatorly.
So I flipped these
around. So pay attention
to this one. So I didn't
put it on the same side.
Maybe I should have.
I'm not, I didn't do
it to make you confused.
But in this case,
this is a secretion,
right? Because it's
going from basal
lateral to interstitial.
It does so by one characterized
and one mysterious way.
Urea goes from the
basal side into the
cell via this UTA2
urea transporter
family of proteins. And
then once inside the,
in the cytosol, then
again, it will go out
into the urine by,
by another member of,
of this family of
transporters, the UTA2.
The other one is a mystery,
and really nobody really
knows how. How do we
know? It's, um it's a
transporter it exhibits
saturation kinetics and similar
hallmarks to what we saw
with glucose so the rest
of the reabsorption occurs
in the collecting duct
again that's also transcellular
and we're going back
to the normal luminal
versus basolateral this is
reabsorption right so
whenever we're talking about
luminal to basolateral
we're talking reabsorption
And again, it uses one of
these urea transporters,
UTA1, to get into the
cytosol, and then UTA3 to
leave the cytosol and go
into the interstitial.
So normal urine flow
and hydration status,
it's 50% of the
filter load, but that
changes depending on
those two variables.
So that's one product that
you can find from amino
acids. What about amino
acids themselves? What
about non-metabolized amino
acids? We do have amino
acids in our blood, around
2.5 millimolar is the
average concentration you
find in the plasma, and
this is mostly due to
absorption by the GI tract.
Other parts of it are
either, you know, products
of protein catabolism,
or if you have de novo
synthesis of non-essential
amino acids. Remember,
essential talks about its
ability to behave through
the diet.
Amino acids are freely
filtered into glomerulus, and
they are also reabsorbed to
a very high degree. Again,
100% filtered load in our
Bowman's capsule. Almost
all of it is reabsorbed
in the proximal convoluted
tubule, 99% more. So by the
time you get to the urine,
it's almost nothing left.
There are small amounts in
the collecting tubule, in
the medullary collecting
ducts, and in the thin
descending limb, but the lion's
share occurs in the proximal
convoluted tubule. And
it's done so by a variety
of different transporters
and transcellular roots.
And I have them indicated
here. I'm not going to go
through each one. As you
can see, they all will
depend on the concentration
gradient of sodium to get
into the cell, right? Again,
our sodium potassium ATPase is
what gives us the
sodium gradient,
low inside, high outside,
and then amino acids, either
co-transporters or counterporters
will cause the, you
know, will stimulate the
reabsorption of amino acids.
And then the amino acids
are then moved into the The
basolateral side, so either
co-transporters, channels,
or, you know, or different
antiporters. Again,
knowing the individual ones
is not as important as knowing
that it's the sodium gradient
is what drives almost
everything in this context.
I mean, the only one that
you can probably say doesn't
are these channels for
phenylalanine, tryptophan,
and tyrosine. but again
nobody expects you to know
the distinction between the
different amino acids and
how they get from the luminal
side into the interstitial
side unless you decide to
you know go and study tubular
mechanisms of reabsorption
and which is a lot
of fun but again
that's not neither
here or there
So amino acids, what's
one level above amino
acids? Well, oligopeptides.
And these are not
proteins. These are multi
-amino acid, you know,
peptides, anywhere
between 2 to 20 residues
of amino acids. And
you find a lot of
them, you know, a
lot of our hormones,
vasoactive hormones are
for chain peptides.
Glutathione, which is a
major antioxidant molecule
in our body, is a, you
know, a three amino acid
peptide. So there are a
lot of oligopeptides in the
plasma. And again, so
they get filtered and they
are small enough to get
through the charge barrier
and they have to get
reabsorbed. And again, the
proximal convoluted tubule
does, you know, more
than 99% of the filtered
load of oligopeptides
and the rest of it is
reabsorbed in the proximal
straight tubule, and
the rest of the nephrons
contribute very little
to peptide transport.
Now, how does this work?
Two different mechanisms.
The first one requires its
metabolism to amino acids.
And this happens by the
actions of brush border
peptidases. Now you remember our
brush borders on them? You
can have, you can see the
huge surface area that one
sees on the brush border.
And imagine all these
peptidases that are facing the
urine. And here it'll take
the peptides and metabolize
them and breaks them
apart into smaller pieces.
Now, these are a lot of
different types of peptidases.
Imminopeptidases,
endopeptidase, dipeptidase,
eggs. There's just a
lot of them. And so
many of them that they
actually don't even name
them. They just have
letter designations.
And they will break the
oligopeptide to their small
individual, to their individual
amino acid components,
and then the amino acid
will just jump in on the
amino acid transporter,
the sodium amino acid
transporters, and get located
into the cytosol and then
leaves the cytosol via
different amino acid channels.
The other way is the
peptidase is inside
the cell, and the
oligopeptide will, in
this case, sorry,
that's really horrible,
but yeah, I apologize for that.
The oligopeptide
gets into the cell
via a transporter,
an oligopeptide
proton co-transporter
called PEPT1 or PEPT2,
and inside the cell,
you have intercellular
peptidases that will
break it apart, and
then the amino acid will
then leave the cell.
So PEPT1 is a low
affinity, high capacity
transporter, and PEPT2 is a
high affinity, low capacity
transporter. It binds
really well because there's
so little oligopeptides
getting in. And PEPT1
is, will bind a lot
of different types of
oligopeptides. So all of it
will lead to amino acids.
And, and which ones
get digested in the
lumen versus the ones
that get into the cell,
that is really not
something that's known.
So breakdown of amino
acids, amino acids,
oligopeptides. How
about proteins? Well,
the GFR, the
glomerification barrier
prevents the filtration
of large amounts
of protein, especially
larger proteins.
So it doesn't eliminate it.
You just have very, very
little getting through.
So, you know, when it
comes to large proteins,
and remember, albumin
is the largest, is one
of the larger ones, and
it's also more, one of
the, you know, more
abundant plasma proteins,
96, 99% of it is
reabsorbed in the proximal
convoluted tubing.
So you have very
little in the urine,
but it's not zero.
They also, again,
that's one of the bigger
ones, low molecular
rate proteins are also
reabsorbed. And how they're
reabsorbed is not
through channels.
It's done by a mechanism,
is by endocytosis and
specifically receptor
mediated endocytosis to
reabsorb the proteins and
polypeptides. And again, it
occurs in the proximal
convoluted tumor because
we have such a large surface
area. So what happens?
Any kind of protein
that gets filtered, that
makes it through the
glomerular filtration barrier,
will interact through
different areas, different
parts of the sequence
to specific areas on the
plasma membrane. And these
are called coded pits.
And one of the more common
ones is a clathrin-coated
pit, which is important
for protein reabsorption.
So once the protein binds
to this coated pit, it
gets internalized. The pit
will basically invaginate,
bind, and take the protein
and everything with it
into the cell. There, it'll
bind with an endosome,
and then with a lysosome,
and all of them together,
you know, especially
things like lysosome,
where you have a higher
pH, and peptidases will
start breaking apart
the protein and then
releasing the individual
amino acids into the
cytosol. Well, they'll
get reabsorbed back into,
back into the
interstitial space.
Because it requires,
you know, membrane,
you know, formation, vesicular
formation, Internalization,
that's energy of using
process, and cell movement
is always microtubular
involved. So any kind of a
metabolic poison that inhibits
those pathways will stop
the reabsorption of large
proteins. So either metabolic
inhibitors or these mycotoxins
like cytocholacin B.
Cytocholacin B is a fungal
alkaloid that will basically
stop any kind of microtubular
-associated movement.
So those can, you know,
block this effect, and you
will see substantial amounts
of protein in the urine.
Now, you can see that in
people if they go foraging
for mushrooms, and if they,
you know, will eat
a look-alike that
they don't know,
and they'll have all
these, you know,
horrible effects.
But one of the, you know, modes
of diagnosis is like looking at
proteinuria to give you an
idea of where the damage is.
So, these are the
specific metabolites, but
I wanted to talk about
these two systems that
are very, very important
in the kidney for
either secretion or
reabsorption of classes of
compounds. And these
are the organic acid
and the organic base
secretory systems.
So what happens, any
kind of an organic
acid, anything that
RCO negative, you know,
and it doesn't matter
what the R is, what
the R group is, you
know, if it's got a
acidic moiety, that's
considered to be
an organic acid.
That could be an
endogenous compound,
it could be a drug,
you know, these are all
become, will get secreted into,
filtered and then secreted
into the lumen and
reabsorbed, all very
much dependent on what
you're talking about. But
a lot of these organic
acids are products of
metabolite and glucose,
fatty acid metabolism,
so getting them back
is very important for
energy metabolism.
And basically,
you know, call them
carboxylate, anything that's
got a carboxylate. And
And it has a key M,
so when these compounds
hit their membrane limit,
you can have, you'll find
remnants of them in the
urine. Ketone bodies are
organic acids that are
the result of fatty acid
metabolism, and you can
detect them in the urine
if you have excess fatty
acid breakdown, which
can happen in glucose, in
diabetes. It can also
happen in severe exercise.
You can, you know, you become
ketotic. This is what happens.
So you don't have to
know the individual ones.
It's just a system.
So these are done by a
variety of different solute
carriers, both on the
apical and on the basolateral
side. And depending
on which one it is,
they can go either way.
And they overlap in their
substrate specificity.
So they're very non
-selective. Again, as
long as it's an organic
acid and you have to
excrete it, it will go
through these systems.
One of them is one of
the common ones that we
can use to measure renal
function is para-aminohipurate,
PAH, and you've
talked about that in
concept of clearance.
It's a water, it's a water
-soluble organic anion or
organic, you know, acid,
they're synonymous, right?
OA, it works, right? Organic
acid secretory system
or, you know, organic
anion secretory system.
And at low plasma
concentrations, we can
use PAH experimentally
to measure renal
plasma flow, and it
will actually give you a
value called effective
renal plasma flow.
So another type of organic
acid that's also excreted
is uric acid. Uric acid
also will jump on a
lot of these transporters,
but these organic
acid transporters, the
oats. Again, there's
a lot of them. You
don't have to know them.
But again, you know, uric acid
undergoes both reabsorption
and secretion. You can see
the secretion down here.
So
there is a ATP-dependent
uric acid transporter.
You can see this
here, the BCRP.
The BCRP will take
your uric acid from the
cytosol and push it
into the urine. There
is an uncharacterized
pathway also called
NPT-104 using a
transporter called NPT-104
and MRP. These are all
secretory mechanisms. The
reabsorption happens through
OATS and through this
uric acid transporter,
and then the uric acid
transporter, one of the
variations of it ends up removing
uric acid and taking it
back into the plasma.
Those are the acids. What
about the bases? Well, the
organic, there is a system
very similar, and it's
not as extensive. So you
have, again, 100% of it is in
the filtered load, and a
variable amount of organic
bases get secreted into the
nephron. And these could
be organic, and again, I've
said organic base secretory
system. It could also be,
it's also called organic,
as I call it, yeah, it
should be OB, I'm sorry,
OBSS.
You either call it an
organic base or organic
cation secretory system.
So those are synonymous.
These are important
for endogenous
cations, things like
dopamine, epinephrine,
norepinephrine, histamine,
anything, you know, any
of those compounds that
remains in the blood and it's
not metabolized can get
secreted into the urine.
The most important one
obviously is creatinine,
which is the breakdown
product of phosphocreatinine,
and we use creatinine
to give us an
estimation of our GFR. So
anything that can affect
the secretion of creatinine
into the nephron can give us
variations in our
ability to measure
GFR. Again, a big part
of drug secretion,
morphine, you know,
is, uses the organic
base circuitry
system to get into,
into the nephron.
Atropine, you know,
quinine, which is an anti
-malarial. The most important
one that, you know, you
should remember is the
potassium sparing diuretics.
Potassium sparing diuretics,
amylride triamptory,
remember they work on
the distal convoluted
tubule. They require the
organic base secretory
system to get into the
nephron and have diuretic
efficacy. If they don't
get into the nephron, they
can't bind to their target
channels. So it becomes
very, very important
for their functionality.
So this table kind of breaks
down what endogenous, exogenous
capabilities of
organic and of the
secretion by the
proximal tubule.
So some, you know,
for example, and, you
know, bile salts
members of, you know,
citric acid cycle, fatty
acids, ragiuric acid.
These are all anions that
get secreted endogenously.
Catiions indicated some
of that. Creatinine
does both because it
depends on its charge.
And exogenous, you know,
almost almost all the
diuretics we use for clinical
practice, almost all,
not all, are secreted by
the organic anion secretory
system into the nephron.
Exception, ameloride and
triamterine, the two
potassium sparing diuretics.
Some of the NSAIDs that we
use, indometicin, salicylate,
non-steroidal anti
-inflammatory drugs.
And then penicillin G
is one that is secreted
and a compound called
probenicid, which we use in
a variety of different
clinical scenarios to
inhibit the activity of
the organic acid secretory
system. In fact, probenicid
was first developed
to save penicillin in the
urine. When penicillin
G was first developed,
it was right in the
middle of World War
II, and they have not
ramped up the amounts
made for the use in war.
So they needed every
microgram of penicillin that
was made, and you end up
secreting a lot of it in
the urine. How do you stop
doing that? Well, they
found out that by giving
probenicid, you inhibit
the secretion of penicillin
G into the nephron. And
you can actually lower
dose of penicillin for
people because you don't
get rid of it as much. So
you end up having efficacy
by increasing the potency
of penicillin in the
amounts that's in the body.
Of course, if you did
that and somebody had
a UTI, then you're blocking
its effects because
that's where you need
penicillin to work.
So it's both good and bad.
And anything that
comes out of the phase
two of our drug
metabolism pathways,
you know, the
pharmacokinetics of drugs,
glucuronation and
glutathioneation, sulfation, all
phase one metabolic processes
that once they're done,
they can actually help
the drug to get excreted.
So let's go back to this.
So, you know, high sugar,
young age, she finds into
the demographic and she
is, you know, your young
patient is diagnosed as
type one diabetes mellitus.
and you know that's because
their blood sugar is
very very high at that
instant her you know she had
normal glycemia uh mainly
because probably probably
not mainly probably because
um she wasn't eating
anything she did so and
whatever uh amount of glucose
that she had she was she
was losing it. So, and that
would act as a diuretic,
stay in the glucose,
drive more water out, and
patient became dehydrated, and
then you had fatigue
and lethargy.
Look at your feedback
form, and the next
two lectures we'll
talk about acid base,
and then we finalize
by talking about
the kidney and its
ability to concentrate
and dilute depending
on the situations.
All right. Thank
you, everybody.